There's something that a lot of people
do when they're working with AI to
create code that totally drives me
crazy. And it's sort of something that
I've been railing against for a while
now. The thing that I've noticed is
people tend to think I need to create a
spec for AI. I need to create a plan,
right? Plan mode, spec-driven
development. I need to put all of my
efforts into making this extremely
detailed spec so that when I get some
outputs from the AI, those outputs are
going to look like the spec. I'm going
to have specified everything up front so
that I can just perfectly nail it. And
in this impulse, what they forget to do
is they forget they can actually write
code. You can write code while you're
working towards a spec. Prototyping and
spikes are things that we've had around
since the days of Agile, right? I mean,
I suppose these are still the days of
Agile. Agile is still extremely popular,
still extremely influential. But people
just aren't prototyping anymore. And so,
as part of my skills repo, I'm trying to
turn this around. I have a prototype
skill. A prototype is throwaway code
that answers a question. Everyone is
saying that code is cheap, and it's
partially true and partially I hate that
phrase. But the thing that is cheap is
the cost of producing code has gone way,
way down. So, producing prototypes,
producing quick kind of throwaway spikes
has never been cheaper and never been a
more effective tool. In this video, I'm
going to introduce this prototype skill.
I'm going to talk about when you should
use it, what it can be used for, and
also how it fits into my new wayfinder
skill. But first, to explain the concept
of fidelity, high fidelity and low
fidelity. Whenever you're talking about
designing something, you're going to
have questions in your mind that need to
be resolved somehow. Some of the
questions are going to be really basic,
like the basic frame of the thing you're
building. When the modal opens up, it
should have a cancel button and a
confirm button, simple stuff. With
simple stuff like that, you don't need a
lot of high fidelity stuff to answer the
question. That can just be resolved in
discussion, really. But let's say that
the modal, when it opens up, under some
circumstances it needs to show some
data, you might need to go a little bit
of higher fidelity on that. How would
you display the data? It's often hard
when you're planning out a spec to
figure out exactly how things should
look, and how things should look, how
they should behave under certain
circumstances, making sure that you've
road tested all of this idea in kind of
semi working code, that means you need a
higher fidelity. Some questions really
can only be answered by prototyping. And
because producing these prototypes is
now cheaper than it ever has been
before, I tend to want more of my
discussions at a higher fidelity.
Obviously, the basic stuff I'm going to
just resolve through discussion. So, the
agent is going to ask me some questions,
probably through a grilling session, and
then I'm going to say, "Okay, yeah, this
sounds good." But then, as soon as we
get anything that I think, "Oh, I really
need to see this in action. I need to
feel it in action, look at it working."
I'm going to ask for a prototype.
Prototyping is a part of my new
Wayfinder skill, which is a skill that
allows you to plan a huge chunk of work.
There's a future video coming on
Wayfinder. Now, Wayfinder, what it does
is it tackles a huge chunk of work, and
it splits it up into different planning
sessions. And all of these planning
sessions get their own ticket, and there
should be somewhere in here ticket
types, just here, that tells it exactly
what different ticket types there are.
The two that we're looking at here are
the grilling type, so it's using the
grilling skills, and the prototype
ticket type. The default case here is
the grilling type, so where you're
chatting with the agent, figuring out
the basic scope of the thing you're
building. But when you need to raise the
fidelity of the discussion, making a
cheap, rough, concrete artifact to react
to, an outline, a rough take a stab at
UI logic code via the prototype skill,
links the prototype as an asset, use
when how should it look or how should it
behave is is key question. Whether
you're using Wayfinder not, this gives
you a really clear criteria for when you
should reach for a prototype. So, I'm
sure you're dying to see it in action,
and here it is. This is what it's done.
I've been using Wayfinder to extend my
diagramming app here, which is built on
TLDraw. And I wanted a way to search
through old diagrams, and the data model
here is quite complicated. There's like
diagrams and then snapshots of the
diagram through time. And so, I wanted
to build a search bar, but I wasn't sure
how it should look or behave. So, I ran
prototype here, and what it did is it
created this little uh
picker at the bottom here. And this
picker, if I go between it, it has three
different options. So, that's option B,
and that's option C. And each one
encodes a few design decisions that I
can then react to and iterate on. So,
let's start by looking at A. I've just
generated this. I've not actually looked
at it yet. So, I get to search the
diagrams and see what comes up. And this
one, okay, it's reflow in place grouped
rows. So, it's grouping the snapshots by
the name of the diagram. I really like
the placing of the search box up here,
but this grouping doesn't feel right to
me. So, let's see what B is. Let's
search again inside model here, and
okay, now on the left, we have grouping
for where it can filter down. Okay,
that's quite nice. What happens if I
search for something else and it's
already Okay, so the filter resets at
that point. Now, that's okay, but I
wonder what C looks like. I really don't
like this search diagrams thing at the
top. That doesn't look nice, but let's
see what this looks like. So, let's
search for model, and ooh, okay, so now
it's everything in line, no filters. So,
I do actually really like this, but
there are a few things that I don't
like. I don't like these current things.
It looks like this is really technical
weird thing, but the the current one is
showing with the diagram snapshot. So,
I've got some kind of feedback that I I
to give to the prototype. This
prototyping session took about 100,000
tokens. So, I'm actually going to
compact and say, "We're going to do some
more QA on this." Compacting at this
point makes sense to me because we kind
of need to retain all of the information
about the prototype, need to retain all
of the design decisions that went into
it, but we just need to give it some
feedback. So, we just need to continue
the conversation in the same place in
the codebase. I should definitely do a
video about the design tree that I use
for when I've got compact versus clear
versus handoff, but, you know, that's
one for another time. Okay, now I'm
going to give some feedback. I really
like the search box of A and I like the
layout of C. Okay, so I've just dictated
in some more feedback and I'm going to
send it off. So, the idea of this
session is that I'm iterating on this
prototype. I'm not just saying, "Okay,
this is the best one." I'm going to
actually create some design decisions
here, create a super rich asset. All of
these design decisions are then going to
be encoded into the prototype and I'm
going to save the prototype probably on
a throwaway branch. That means that when
the thing actually goes to implement it,
it's not only got a spec, it's actually
got real front-end code that it can
usually copy and paste out of it. Now,
creating these prototypes does take some
time, right? The higher fidelity you go,
the more token cost there is. If we were
to try to resolve this in a discussion,
we'd be at a lower fidelity, so the
answers would be less useful, but we'd
also be spending fewer tokens. And we
can see it's now starting to give me a D
version here, which is kind of what I've
been iterating towards. One note here is
that this is actually
integrated with the live page. So, it's
not doing this on a throwaway route. You
can do that if you want to, but I really
like seeing it actually plugged into the
live route because then it just gives
you so much more flexibility. It it like
it's a more honest representation of how
the code is actually going to work. All
right, looks like it is now created D,
so let's see what that looks like. Yes,
we have the box from A and if we search
in here with model, then we can see that
everything I asked for actually got
done. Before we had a duplicate of this
one, but now there's only one. And in
theory, if I click this, I'm not sure if
this will actually work. I don't know
whether this is part of the prototype.
Yes, it works. Oh, beautiful. So, there
we go. Loads of this functionality looks
like it is now just done. And so, you
might ask, what is the next step after
this? Well, now I consider the prototype
to be complete. That was a pretty quick
one. Usually, I'm kind of in here doing
a lot more. Um I would pass this off to
an AFK agent to plug in everything,
delete the old prototype code, and just
make sure that it was uh compliant with
the original spec. And as you can
imagine, the results here are incredible
because we've had such high fidelity
discussion, because we've been able to
look at a live running version of it,
give our feedback based on that. That
feedback is so invaluable, and it's
already baked into a throwaway branch
that our implementer can actually just
go and reference. So many times I see
people saying, well, the thing didn't
build what I wanted. I created this big,
beautiful spec, and it just did
something totally weird. You probably
just weren't having discussions at a
high enough fidelity, and you probably
should have been prototyping. Finally, I
don't want you to walk away thinking
this is only for UI or front-end stuff.
Front-end definitely benefits a lot from
prototypes because how should it look,
what should it look like is a really key
question that's really hard to answer
during the discussion phase. However,
when you're doing more complicated
stuff, especially back-end work, then a
question like, does this logic, does
this state model feel right? If you're
building anything reasonably complex or
that needs to work in the real world,
then you're going to run into these
questions all the time. And often, the
best way to get around these kind of
questions to build something that kind
of serves the needs of your users,
especially on something complex, is to
build a prototype. Now, it doesn't need
to be a UI prototype. And what I've got
here is build a tiny interactive
terminal app that pushes the state
machine through cases that are hard to
reason about on paper. In other words, a
pure logic prototype. And I've had tons
of feedback from folks saying that this
is such a nice little feature. Both of
these branches have their own reference
docs here, which tell it exactly how to
do each one. So, if it's building a
logic prototype, it looks here. If it's
building a UI prototype, it looks like
this. So, I beg of you, have your
discussions at a higher fidelity. As
agents get better at working with
canvases, working with design tools, I'm
sure that wireframes will definitely
make a comeback as well. And the key
point is this, the leap from discussion
and spec to production-ready code is
really big. Whereas, if you have a
working prototype, turning that into
production is pretty simple. I want to
give a quick shout-out to Shape Up by
Ryan Singer, which is an extremely good
book and very, very influential on me. I
read this, I think, in 2019 or
something, and it totally changed the
way that I built applications for
people. It is totally free online, and I
will drop a link in the description. If
you want to keep up-to-date with my
skills, then my skills newsletter is the
place to be. I'm shipping, shipping,
shipping, constantly thinking about
these skills, how I can make them
better, and you can benefit from that
the day that I make the changes. But
folks, thank you so much for watching.
It's been a pleasure, as always,
bringing you one of my skills, and I
will see you very soon.